A Guide to the Papers of Benjamin Griffith Brawley, 1928-1938
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Benjamin Griffith Brawley 1928-1938
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9498-b
This collection consists of 86 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Papers of Benjamin Griffith Brawley were removed from the Papers of the Dillard Family, MSS 9498, April 2006 and accessioned separately. The Papers of the Dillard Family were originally deposited in the Library by Hardy Cross Dillard, Charlottesville, Va. on July 13, 1970. The Papers were made a gift by Valgerdur Nielsen Dillard, Richmond, Va. in October, 2003.
Biographical/Historical Information
Benjamin Griffith Brawley was born April 22, 1882, in Columbia, S.C. and died of a stroke, February 1, 1939, in Washington, D.C. He was the son of Edward MacKnight Brawley and Margaret Dickerson Brawley. Brawley married Hilda Damaris Prowd, July 20, 1912.
Brawley received a B.A. from Atlanta Baptist College (now Morehouse College), in 1901; a B.A. from the University of Chicago, in 1906; and, an M.A. from Harvard University in 1908. He taught in a rural one-room school in Florida 1901-1902. From 1902 until 1910 he served as an instructor in English and Latin at Morehouse College, Atlanta, Georgia. In 1910, Brawley moved to Washington, D.C. where he was appointed professor of English at Howard University. He returned to Morehouse College in 1912 where he remained until 1920. He was ordained as a Baptist minister in 1921 and served at Messiah Baptist Church, Brockton, Massachusetts in 1921 and 1922.
In 1923, Brawley was appointed professor of English at Shaw University in Raleigh, North Carolina. He became Dean at Shaw in 1930. Brawley left Raleigh in 1931 to accept a position as professor of English at Howard University in Washington, D.C. He remained at Howard until his death in 1939.
Benjamin Brawley, a prolific author, is best known for his works in literary and social history. Among his books that were once standard texts in college and university curricula are The Negro in Literature and Art in the United States, New Survey of English Literature, and two biographical volumes, The Negro Genius, and Negro Builders and Heroes. Brawley was also the author of short stories and poems and editor of The Best Stories of Paul Laurence Dunbar. He contributed scholarly articles to the Dictionary of American Biography and published historical essays, social commentaries, poems, and book reviews in prominent periodicals such as The Crisis, The Dial, Bookman, Southern Workman, Opportunity, The Journal of Negro History, and Harvard Monthly. While at Shaw University, Brawley was the editor of The Home Mission College Review for several years.
James Hardy Dillard was born in Nansemond County, Virginia October 24, 1856 and died in Charlottesville, Virginia on August 2, 1940. He was the son of James and Sara Cross Dillard. He married Mary Harmanson of Norfolk, Virginia on July 5, 1882. He married Avarene Lippincott Budd of Mt. Holly, New Jersey on November 19, 1899.
Dillard graduated from Washington and Lee University in 1876 and taught mathematics there for a year. From 1877 to 1882, he served as principal of the Rodman School in Norfolk, Virginia. Between 1882 and 1891, he served as joint principal of Norfolk Academy and as a faculty member at the following institutions: the University of Vermont, Phillips Exeter Academy, the State Normal School in Oswego, New York, and Mary Institute, the woman's department of Washington University in St. Louis.
Dillard was appointed professor of Latin at Tulane University in New Orleans in 1891. In 1904, he was selected to serve as dean of the academic colleges, a position he held until 1907. While in New Orleans, Dillard became deeply involved in numerous social and educational endeavors and worked for improved race relations and educational opportunities for African Americans. He was chosen to be the first president and director of the Negro Rural School Fund (a.k.a. the Anna T. Jeanes Fund), positions he held from 1907 until 1931. From 1910 to 1917, Dillard served as the director of the John F. Slater Fund; from 1917 until 1931 he served as the Fund's president. At various times, Dillard served on the board of the Phelps Stokes Fund, Leland University, Southern University, Straight University, and New Orleans University. Dillard University, formed in 1934 from the merger of Straight and New Orleans universities, was named in Dillard's honor.
Scope and Content
This collection consists chiefly of letters from Benjamin Brawley to James Hardy Dillard concerning the writing and publication of Brawley's book, Doctor Dillard of the Jeanes Fund. Other topics mentioned include Shaw University, Howard University, the Jeanes and Slater Funds, the General Education Board, and Dillard University. Other correspondents include Anson Phelps Stokes, Leo M Favrot, and Trevor Arnett. Of interest is a letter, 1936 January 21, in which Brawley discusses his collecting of "Negro literature."
Contents List
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1928 June 25, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:1)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for the notes he sent; mentions Wallace Buttrick and says a quote from him inspired the title of Brawley's biography of Dillard; asks Dillard to answer the enclosed questions [not present].
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1928 July 14, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:2)
  Brawley hopes that Dillard has recovered from his illness; mentions discrepancies in biographical sources and says he has been "soaking" himself in reading about Washington and Lee and wants Dillard to "tell me about the men there who impressed you most between 1873 and 1877."
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1928 July 28, TLS, 2 p. (Box-folder 1:3)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for letting him see "these letters" [not present]; he mentions that he has talked to Jackson Davis, who offered sources of information about Dillard. Brawley mentions the Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences and says that he was asked to write entries on Dillard and "General Armstrong" [Samuel Chapman Armstrong]. Brawley says that "four conventions of Negro Baptists" will meet in Raleigh next week to celebrate the sixtieth anniversary of the state convention. He mentions his travel schedule and closes with wishes for Dillard's improved health.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1928 July 29, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:4)
  The article "The Southern tradition" will be published in the September issue of The North American Review and Brawley will be sure that Dillard receives a copy.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1928 September 4, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:5)
  Brawley sends wishes for Dillard's improved health.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1928 September 26, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:6)
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1928 September 28, ALS, 2 p. (Box-folder 1:7)
  Brawley urges Dillard to follow his doctors' advice and avoid traveling this winter. He thanks Dillard for a suggestion about the book title and tell him that Jackson Davis, Thomas Jesse Jones and "Mr. Caldwell" have offered assistance on "special topics." Brawley says the text should be finished by "late winter or early spring" and ask Dillard to consider writing a foreword.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1928 October 2, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:8)
  Brawley writes to "make correction about the impression that has gone abroad about Dr. Klein's report on Negro colleges." Brawley states that the first pamphlet is only the introduction and that "separate chapters are to be given to different states." He thanks Dillard for allowing him to see a letter from "Dr. Moton" [Robert Russa Moton] [not present] and encloses a letter from "Dr. Stokes"[Anson Phelps Stokes?] [not present].
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1928 October 19, ALS, 3 p. (Box-folder 1:9)
  Brawley discusses the article "A School of the Past" and praises Dillard. He asks Dillard for "insight into your work as a teacher" and emphasizes the need for this point of view in his book. He closes by saying that copies of The Home Mission College Review will be mailed to Dillard shortly.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1928 October 29, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:10)
  Brawley returns a letter [not present] and asks if Dillard might have some photographs from his early career.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1928 December 21, ALS, 2 p. (Box-folder 1:11)
  Brawley proposes to send his manuscript to Dillard "to have the benefit of your criticism and opinion before the work begins to take final shape." Brawley will be leaving for Washington on Tuesday and plans to see Dillard in Charlottesville on Monday, December 31.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1929 January 10, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:12)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for the assistance he gave during Brawley's visit to Charlottesville; he thanks Dillard for his recent letter and says he wants to make "this book the most helpful one I have ever written."
- [Thomas Jesse Jones] to Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C., 1929 January 12, TL, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:13)
  "Copy to Dr. Dillard" written in pencil above salutation. Jones apologizes to Brawley for his failure to send material for Brawley's book. He mentions his esteem for Dillard and encloses a "memorandum" [not present] to show "the kind of statement which I would like to prepare."
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1929 January 19, ALS, 2 p. (Box-folder 1:14)
  Brawley encloses a card [not present] with notes about appropriations from the Slater Fund and asks Dillard "just what is the point about Shaw?" He says that the "actual working of the system makes no real difference in the teacher's salary." He says that he is paid from the college office like all other Shaw employees and that "Shaw now has no special Slater teacher." Brawley has received material from Thomas Jesse Jones and "Mr. Kearny" and hopes to have the manuscript to the publisher by March.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1929 January 24, ALS, 3 p. (Box-folder 1:15)
  Brawley asks if Dillard has "an unpublished paper on your impressions of Africa" and mentions other material he has recently read. He still hopes to have the manuscript to the publisher for fall publication. Brawley says that he understands the purpose of the Slater Fund assistance is "to help raise the general standard by seeing to it that at least one teacher is adequately paid." He says that he is receiving $250 less than Dillard intended and has never been paid more than $2000 "at any place at which I have taught." He "could not exist if it were not for summer work or an occasional article. But there is also the moral question if I have been treated justly." Brawley asks Dillard for his assistance.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1929 January 26, ALS, 2 p. (Box-folder 1:16)
  Brawley concurs with Dillard's "reply to Dr. Patton" and mentions his A Social History of the American Negro. Brawley encloses English exam papers [not present] for Dillard's review. He mentions "Mr. Kearny" and "Mr. Newbold" [Nathan Carter Newbold?]
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1929 January 31, ALS, 3 p. (Box-folder 1:17)
  Brawley asks Dillard to publish his article, "The Case of Kenya," in the Home Mission College Review instead of in The Atlantic. He explains that he asked Mr. Newbold to read the introduction. Brawley tells Dillard that Newbold's son is on trial for hitting and killing a man with his automobile. He then tells Dillard that the "Negro bank, a branch of the one in Durham," was robbed of $4000 but fortunately there was no run on the bank "for the Negroes of Raleigh, by way of showing their confidence, made special deposits and drew out very little money." The loss is covered by insurance and the "white banks in the city were quick to offer any assistance needed." Brawley closes by saying "Hampton is at present a case of lack of coherence. It is hard to write about the situation there; but if there should be opportunity at any time soon, I should be glad to talk it over."
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., [1929 January?], ANS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:18)
  Brawley asks Dillard to send reprints of three articles. A note in Dillard's hand indicates two copies of the requested articles were sent on February 2.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1929 February 1, ALS, 2 p. (Box-folder 1:19)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for "the concluding page of the Kenya article." The rest of the letter is a discussion of Shaw students' performance in English classes.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1929 February 11, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:20)
  Brawley asks Dillard for a photograph of "Mr. Slater" [John F. Slater] and says he also wants to obtain a photograph of "Miss Jeanes" [Anna Jeanes]. He asks Dillard to keep him informed of his "movements early in March" since Brawley hopes to send the completed manuscript to Dillard.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1929 February 27, ALS, 2 p.; with TN, 1 p., 1929 March 1. (Box-folder 1:21)
  Brawley tells Dillard he is sending the book manuscript "to-day." He is still waiting for the picture of "Miss Jeanes." Brawley has sent copies of The Home Mission College Review and hopes to send The English Journal shortly. He concludes by telling Dillard he would like to have "the Kenya article" for the Review. The attached typed note acknowledges receipt of the book manuscript and informs Brawley that Dillard is out of town.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1929 March 18, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:22)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for the "kind word about the Kenya article" and for considering "writing to Dr. Moton [Robert Russa Moton] about the quotation." Brawley says he has just returned from giving a lecture at Hampton.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1929 March 30, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:23)
  Brawley has received the manuscript from Dillard and has sent it to New York. He thanks Dillard for his notes and is glad there are no major changes to make. He has made the change in the Moton quotation that Dillard suggested.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1929 April 2, ALS, 3 p. (Box-folder 1:24)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for "the suggestion about Scribner's" and says he is obliged by his last contract with Knopf to let them see his next book. He mentions that his students at Shaw presented a play and "the whole performance was the best we have ever had." Brawley will be happy for Dillard to see the proofs of the book and thanks him for sending a photograph. Brawley has just mailed a review of "Dr. Jones's new book" [Essentials of Civilization by Thomas Jesse Jones?].
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1929 May 16, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:25)
  Brawley has mailed 30 copies of the May issue of The Home Mission College Review containing Dillard's article. He hopes the book will be published by Christmas.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1929 June 14, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:26)
  Brawley says that "'Dillard University' is very gratifying to me. We shall have to include that in the book." He mentions that Anson Phelps Stokes has agreed to write a special introduction. Brawley concludes by telling Dillard he has declined Howard University's offer. He does not "feel that my best service and best development lie in that direction."
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1929 September 20, ALS, 3 p. (Box-folder 1:27)
  Brawley is glad to know that Dillard is safely returned from his European trip. Brawley tells Dillard that the book manuscript is being read by Doubleday, Doran & Co. He apologizes for the time lost in having sent the manuscript, at the suggestion of Anson Phelps Stokes, to Yale University Press. Brawley has sent Dillard a copy of Freshman Year English and will soon send a copy of the new edition of The Negro in Literature and Art.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1929 December 7, ALS, 3 p. (Box-folder 1:28)
  Brawley explains that the terms offered by Doubleday, Doran & Co. were unacceptable; he needs more time but is confident of having the published properly published. Brawley seconds Dillard's hope "that Hampton will find the man she needs." He mentions Baptist Home Mission work, "Dr. White," "Dr. Hovey," and "President Peacock" of Shaw University. Brawley says that he feels he is "marking time and I fear the wanderlust has come again and that I am likely at any time to break out and do something rash." He closes by recommending two books (Pedagogically Speaking by Felix Schelling and The American Scholar by Norman Foerster).
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 March 20, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:29)
  Brawley says that publication of the book is set for June 1. The book is to be titled Doctor Dillard of the Jeanes Fund, will be published by Fleming H. Revell and will sell for $1.75. Brawley asks Dillard's opinion on the inclusion of photographs and says he will send Dillard galley proofs.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 March 22, ALS, 3 p. (Box-folder 1:30)
  Brawley comments on an article by Dillard and suggests changes to a sentence about lynching. He mentions the publication of Doctor Dillard of the Jeanes Fund. Brawley says that he wishes he had had time "to go into the matter of Shaw" with Dillard. He says the "college needs a thorough overhauling-physical, mental, spiritual-and I do not feel that it is best for me to work longer under the present situation." Brawley says he has no interest in assuming administrative duties at Shaw. "The institution has a cantankerous and selfish local alumni group that has fought the president mercilessly. Several members of the faculty are not assets. No college in the country is more in need of buildings... ." He closes by saying that "only a stern sense of duty" would compel him to "take up the burden" of reform at Shaw if asked.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 March 24, ALS, 2 p. (Box-folder 1:31)
  Brawley agrees to add a reference to the Slater Fund in the book's preface. He discusses the impact of the proposed title and closes with an anecdote about a French professor at the University of Chicago.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 April 19, ALS, 2 p. (Box-folder 1:32)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for the photographs and discusses the illustrations and their captions. He will send the galley proofs to Dillard shortly and asks Dillard to notify him of any changes or corrections quickly. Brawley mentions that Anson Phelps Stokes "wants to play up the fact that this is a book about a Southern white man written by a Negro." Brawley says he encouraged Stokes "to keep me out of the picture" since he does not think "the proposed statement will encourage white readers in the South to get the book."
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 April 22, ALS, 2 p. (Box-folder 1:33)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for his letter and assures him the book will be "a first class publication." Brawley says there is "another big noise at Shaw." The local alumni group "have just made another attack on the president of the college, this appearing in a local paper." He does not know how the trustees will respond at their upcoming meeting and says "they ought not to overlook the fact that this local group is very eager to run things at the college." He says the alumni "have wanted several things and in each case the college has tried to meet their wishes only to find itself more and more heavily involved in debt."
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charleston, Missouri, 1930 April 29, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:34)
  Brawley apologizes for not getting the proofs to Dillard before he left Charlottesville. Brawley will hold his copy until he hears if Dillard has any changes to make.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 May 8, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:35)
  Brawley discusses illustrations for the book.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 May 6, ALS, 3 p.; with TN, 1 p., 1930 May 8. (Box-folder 1:36)
  Brawley discusses the book illustrations and chapter titles. He mentions the situation at Shaw University and says the president returned from the trustees meeting "somewhat depressed." Brawley says there is a rumor that the president will resign "in the near future." He says that to put the alumni group "in power here would be infinitely worse than any mistake the president has made." The typed note from Dillard's secretary acknowledges receipt of Brawley's letter.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Hampton, Va., 1930 May 13, ALS, 2 p. (Box-folder 1:37)
  Brawley encloses comments on the proofs [not present] by Jackson Davis. Brawley discusses the situation at Shaw University and concludes by saying the "institution must decide just what it its chief function, and then it want to see that the faculty is such as can carry out the main purpose."
- Anson Phelps Stokes to Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C., 1930 May 23, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:38)
  Stokes forwards the text of his introduction [not present] to Doctor Dillard of the Jeanes Fund.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 May 24, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:39)
  Brawley thanks Dillard for his letter and telegram and is pleased that Dillard is happy with the introduction to the book.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 June 12, ALS, 2 p. (Box-folder 1:40)
  Brawley has sent proofs to Anson Phelps Stokes. Brawley has "cut loose from all summer school work" though he is serving as pastor at the White Rock Church in Durham. He says that Jackson Davis indicated the General Education Board will purchase 500 copies of the book.
- Benjamin Brawley, Raleigh, N.C. to Dr. J.[ames] H.[ardy] Dillard, Charlottesville, Va., 1930 July 3, ALS, 3 p. (Box-folder 1:41)